RAJNIKANT YADAV

@ rajnikanty98@gmail.com **** 7007060323 in https://www.linkedin.com/in/rajnikant-yadav/ Lucknow Uttar Pradesh, India https://github.com/rajnikant-yadav

EDUCATION

B.Tech in Electronics and Communication Engineering CGPA: 8.3/10.0

2017-2021

EXPERIENCE

Software Product Developer - I **XLSCOUT**

Mohali

- I specialize in API development for PDFs, XLSX, and Word reports generation on the backend side, manage databases (Postgres, MongoDB, ElasticSearch, Google Cloud Storage), and handle Keycloak integration, SSO, and security tokens.
- I design, implement, maintain, debug, and refactor microservices for patent searching and analysis.
- Conducted automated unit testing and developed interactive API documentation for the Backend application.

Research Analyst Trainee

TT Consultants

Feb 2021 - Jun 2021

Mohali

• As a Research Analyst Trainee at TT Consultants, I conducted Novelty, Invalidation, and Infringement searches.

PYTHON DEVELOPMENT INTERN

Conscript HR Advisors Pvt Ltd

May 2020 - Jul 2020

Work from home

• I wrote Python scripts for data scraping and preprocessing, while also contributing to the development of a Job Aggregator.

MACHINE LEARNING INTERN

Olcademy

M Sept 2019 - Dec 2019

Work from home

- I was involved in developing a discussion forum for Olcademy.
- I contributed to the development of a Pearson Tests of English Simulator.
- I engaged in web scraping and data preprocessing tasks.

PROJECTS

Ecommerce Website

- Developed an E-commerce site using Node.js, React.js, and MongoDB. Enabled user registration, login, product management, and secure transactions with JWT. Leveraged AWS for seamless site hosting and efficient data handling
- TOOL- Node js, ReactJs, Mongodb, AWS, JWT, ExpressJs, Axios

Report Generator API

Aug 2021

- Developed a PDF report generator API that takes login credentials and input queries, downloads images and screenshots from a website, generates a PDF from the text and images, and emails the PDF to the user.
- TOOL -Puppeteer, NodeJs, Fastify, MongoDB, PDFKit, Nodemailer

Sentiment Analysis

Mov 2020

- Developed a model to analyze online text for emotional tone.
- TOOL -Pandas, Python, Beautiful Soup, Matplotlib and LSTM.

ABOUT

A software product developer specializing in modern JavaScript, with hands-on experience in software design and application development, and hands-on experience with cloud infrastructure like AWS and GCP. A quick learner with solid time management and multitasking skills, possessing exceptional troubleshooting and problem-solving abilities, empowered to adapt to diverse situations and contribute to personal and collective growth.

TECHNICAL SKILLS



Programming Languages

JavaScript Pvthon C, C++



Libraries/Frameworks



Tools and Databases

MongoDB MySQL Elasticsearch

CERTIFICATIONS

AWS Architect Associate **Logiclabs Technologies**

Mov 2022 - No Expiration Date

Machine Learning Coursera

Aug 2019 - No Expiration Date

PERSONAL SKILLS

Self Starter Flexible&Adaptable Leadership Communication

EXTRA-CURRICULAR

Crew Member

IEEE

m Sep 2018 - Apr 2019

Technical Head

Technovatorz

Ct 2019 - Present

JUIT: Sports Club member